Guide to the Oregon Social Hygiene Society records
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Oregon Social Hygiene Society records
1895-1960
1911-1940
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Oregon Social Hygiene Society
Mss 1541
6 cubic feet 5 document cases, 13 flat boxes
Records of an Oregon social service organization that was founded in 1911, at the urging of the Young Men's Christian Association, to limit the spread of sexually transmitted diseases and to combat "social vices" such as prostitution, gambling, and childhood immorality. Most files were created by Fred B. Messing, who served as executive secretary from 1929 to 1941. Includes correspondence, subject files, minutes of meetings, financial records, and educational literature.
Collection is open for research.
Gifts of Fred B. Messing in June 1960 and September 1960 (Lib. Acc. 8882).
The collection is arranged in four series:
Series 1: Minutes of meetings, 1911-1938
Series 2: Correspondence, 1915-1960
Series 3: Subject files, 1895-1947
Series 4: Financial records, 1911-1940
The Social Hygiene Society of Portland, Oregon was established in 1911, at the urging of the Young Men's Christian Association, to limit the spread of sexually transmitted diseases and to combat "social vices" such as prostitution, gambling, and childhood immorality. The organization, which was renamed the Oregon Social Hygiene Society in 1913, promoted physical fitness, especially among young people, and exposed medical quackery. It also helped to organize local promotion committees in cities and towns around Oregon. The group focused on educational activities such as lectures, classes, and presentations to school groups, as well as publications, exhibits, government lobbying, and assistance with law enforcement. Committees included: public education, school cooperation, publication, social hygiene, exhibits, social evil, legislation, and quackery. Much of the funding for the organization came from a trust fund established by Dr. E. C. Brown. Its operations were later assumed by the University of Oregon.
Dr. Fred B. Messing was executive secretary of the Oregon Social Hygiene Society from 1929 to 1941. He was born in North Tonawanda, New York, around 1876, and he held a Ph.D. in physical education. Much of his early career was spent working with the YMCA, lecturing on health and sex education to schools, civic organizations, and churches. From 1919 to 1922, he and his wife, Frances, lived in Poland, where Messing directed physical education for the Polish government. After living in Portland for most of his later life, he moved to Chehalis, Washington, where he died in 1960.
Records of the Oregon Social Hygiene Society include correspondence; financial records; lectures; legislation; case histories; minutes (1911-1938); organizational material; society publications and reports; student questions and statements; scrapbooks; and statistics relating to family relations, prostitution, sexual health, and venereal diseases. Correspondence includes letters of Executive Secretary Fred B. Messing. Scrapbooks include photographs of exhibits, publications, letters, and newspaper clippings. Other items include record books, with statistics by city and month, regarding talks, exhibits, and publications to be distributed. Other topics include obscene literature, physical education, contraception, cigarettes, and camps and institutes.
Messing, Fred B.; Messing, Fred B.--Correspondence; Messing, Fred B.
Oregon Social Hygiene Society--Records and correspondence; Social Hygiene Society of Portland, Oregon--Records and correspondence; Social Hygiene Society of Portland, Oregon
Sexual health--Oregon--20th century; Public health--Oregon--Societies, etc.; Public health--Oregon--20th century; Sex instruction--Oregon--20th century; Sex instruction literature--Oregon--20th century
Oregon; Clubs and Societies; Medicine and Health
minutes (administrative records); correspondence; clippings (information artifacts); case histories; scrapbooks
- Minutes of meetings, 1911-1938; Series 1
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1911 September-1912 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1912 January-May (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1912 May-October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes (old volume 4), 1912 November 1-1913 September 6 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Minutes (old volume 5), 1913 September 1-1914 October 9 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Minutes (old volume 6), 1916 April 14-1917 November 9 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Minutes (old volume 7), 1917 November 16-1918 October 25 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Minutes (old volume 8), 1918 November 1-1919 October 31 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Minutes (old volume 9), 1919 November 7-1921 June 3 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Minutes (old volume 10), 1923 September 24-1929 February (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Minutes (old volume 11), 1929 February-October (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee minutes and reports (old volume 12), 1929 September 29-1934 October 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1934-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1915-1960; Series 2
  - General correspondence, 1919; 1929-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence of Fred B. Messing, 1919-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence of Fred B. Messing, 1939-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with members of the Legislature (scrapbook), 1915 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Subject files, 1895-1947; Series 3
  - Camps and institutes, 1911-1940; undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Case histories, 1912-1914; undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Contains anonymous case histories, mostly of young people, regarding sexuality and personal habits.
  - Certificate of appreciation to Fred B. Messing, circa 1941 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Cigarettes, 1940-1947; undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Contraception, 1938; undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Data (old volume 14), 1913; undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Diagnostic tests, 1928-1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes anonymous completed test sheets for the Neymann-Kohlstedt Diagnostic Test for Introversion-Extroversion, 1928 revision.
  - Diaries of Fred and Frances Bell Messing, 1941; undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Typescript diaries, including an account of Fred Messing's travels throughout Oregon in 1941, and his wife's account of the couple's activities in Poland in the early 1920s.
  - Ephemera of Fred B. Messing, 1905-1939; undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lectures by Fred Messing, 1935-1940; undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Legislation, 1912-1940; undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lists, miscellaneous (old volume 19), 1913-1914 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Lists of contributors and other lists (old volume 24), circa 1911-1916 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Marriage, 1928-1938; undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes pamphlets, programs and reports relating to sexual issues in marriage.
  - Membership lists and contributions (old volume 25), 1914-1919 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - News articles and photographs (old volume 23), circa 1928-1937 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Oaths of office, by-laws, and other organizational documents, 1929-1937; undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Obscene literature, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes typescript report on sales of obscene literature in Portland.
  - Physical education, 1900-1939; undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Prostitution, 1932-1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Includes typescript report on commercialized prostitution in Portland, 1932.
  - Publications, 1912-1947; undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Questions/answers, boys, circa 1933-1936; undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Anonymous answers to questions regarding the lectures by the Social Hygiene Society.
  - Questions/answers, girls, circa 1933-1936; undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Record book, 1911-1919 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    Contains monthly statistics, records on frames, talks, circulars, and exhibit attendance.
  - Reports, activity, 1895; 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Reports, annual, 1922-1940 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Reports, miscellaneous, 1910-1940 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Reports, quarterly, monthly, 1911-1939; undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Samples of printed matter (old volume 15), 1914-1917; undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Samples of printed matter (old volume 16), 1917-1919; undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook (old volume 17), 1937-1940 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Contains news clippings, programs and photographs relating to the society's activities.
  - Fred Messing scrapbook (old volume 20), 1899-1907 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - News clippings (old volume 21), 1917-1923 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - News clippings (old volume 22), 1915-1916 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Publications from other sources (old volume 18), 1919-1921; undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "A synopsis of the work of the Oregon Social Hygiene Society", 1911-1915; undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - State record meeting book, 1913-1918 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    Contains city name, committee name, date, attendance numbers, and index.
  - Statistics, miscellaneous, 1899-1939; undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Student addresses, 1931-1939; undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Support statements, 1932-1938; undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Venereal disease, 1912-1939 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Financial records, 1911-1940; Series 4
  - Financial records, general, 1933-1940; undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cash book, 1911-1914 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Cash book, 1917-1920 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Cash book, 1921-1926 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ledger, by account, 1911-1914 (Box 5, Folder 5)